A Guide to the Papers of John Segar Gravatt ca. 1941-1999
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of John Segar Gravatt ca. 1941-1999
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11584
This collection contains ca. 500 items, housed in 2 Hollinger boxes.
This collection consists of the papers of John Segar Gravatt (d. 1983), of Blackstone, Nottoway County, Virginia, ca. 1941-1999, primarily focusing on his interest in the struggle over desegregation of Virginia schools, 1959-1962, and his role as counsel for the Board of Supervisors of Prince Edward County, Virginia, when the decision was made to close the schools in that county.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers were given to the University of Virginia Library by Jacqueline Segar Gravatt of Virginia Beach, Virginia, on February 5, 2000.
Biographical/Historical Information
John Segar Gravatt (d. 1983), of Blackstone, Nottoway County, Virginia, was a member of the Seven Society and graduate from the law school of the University of Virginia in 1933. He also served on the Board of Visitors in the late fifties. He was a student on the football team that played in the first game ever held in Scott Stadium. He also represented Dinwiddie, Nottoway, and Petersburg during the Convention of 1956, which met in Richmond from March 5 to March 7, 1956, and was "called to help implement Virginia's resistance to the United States Supreme Court decision of 1954 barring segregation in the public schools."
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of the papers of Judge John Segar Gravatt (d. 1983), of Blackstone, Nottoway County, Virginia, primarily focusing on his interest in the struggle over the desegregation of Virginia schools, 1959-1962, and his role as counsel for the Board of Supervisors of Prince Edward County, Virginia, when the decision was made to close the schools in that county.
These papers contain news clippings; miscellaneous material concerning desegregation; printed material, much of which was transferred to the Rare Books Division for individual cataloguing; a University of Virginia Board of Visitors docket; a copy of a legal brief, "Griffen v. County School Board of Prince Edward County; some correspondence, many with attached news clippings or other material about the desegregation issue; an article about the Reverend L. Francis Griffin (1917- ) who led the fight for integration of the public schools in Prince Edward County, Virginia; topical files about Civil Rights bills, the Constitutional Convention of Virginia in 1956, Defenders Policy Committee, and Desegregation; reports; a rough draft of a Prince Edward County legal brief; newsletters and form letters; and a photograph of John Segar Gravatt.
Contents List
- Board of Visitors Docket -- University of Virginia 1955 September 9 (Box 1)
- Brief of Griffin v. County School Board of Prince Edward County 1965 September 30 (Box 1)
- Civil Rights Bills 1959 (Box 1)
- Constitutional Convention of the Commonwealth of Virginia 1956 (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1955-1962 (Box 1)
- Defenders Policy Committee 1959-1960 (Box 1)
- "Education in Virginia 1900-1999 A Century of Change" in Richmond Times Dispatch8 August 1999 (Box 1)
- "The Lonely Hero of Virginia School Fight" from Jet Magazine18 May 1961 (Box 18 May 1961)
  re: the Reverend L. Francis Griffin
- Miscellaneous 1955, 1959 (Box 1)
- News clippings 1954-1966, n.d., 3 folders (Box 1)
- Newsletters, Form Letters and Attachments 1953-1960 (Box 1)
- Notebook Material on Desegregation 1941, 1950-1972, 4 folders (Box 2)
- Photograph of John Segar Gravatt n.d. (Box 2)
- Prince Edward County Legal Brief -- Rough Draft n.d. (Box 2)
- Printed Material 1956-1962, n.d. (Box 2)
- Reports 1958, n.d. (Box 2)
- Segregation 1957-1962 (Box 2)